i have a few more questions from around
the world
these two are
related and they
and they
are in terms of
becoming a sotapanna really
so
one friend asks asks
due to an insight that i had a year ago into not-self
into not-self
i take things less personally
and my aversion is rarely minimum
and when it happens it doesn't last long
at all
but i can see that i am still liable to
aversion so my practice right now is holding on
so my practice right now is holding on
to that notion of non-self that i saw
and the non-ownership as the general
background tone of life or the larger
container of things how should i proceed
and this person is actually just
a lay person who's living at home
very kind of relaxed lifestyle
right but
but
beyond that i don't know what they do
well how should i proceed
how should i proceed
it's really more of uh
is there anything else i should do
type of thing
because what's described is uh it's fine
but the question is why why are you
asking yourself how should i proceed
is what you describe is not enough
are you aware there is more to be done
are you not sure about it
if if all these questions persist means
you you can't you can't say you are
beyond doubt
which means you should proceed by doing
more of the same
and then
investigate in what areas
you can improve and you might have been
lacking so maybe you had an insight
so maybe you had an insight
that freed you from sense of ownership
to a degree which is possible you know
to even people who don't
who don't necessarily commit to the
practice 24 7 they could still
experience non-ownership and and
experience release on account of it
but is there is there is there um
is there a cultivation of
of a suitable basis for that insight to
be taken then even further
such as is there a sufficient virtue
accomplishment in virtue sense restraint
seeing the signs of your mind all those
prerequisites basically for a sota
partner people people don't have the
right view not because
you know
dhamma is some secret mystery that they
still haven't figured out
it's because the things that they read
and the things that they understand do
not pertain deeply enough and they don't
pretend deeply enough not because of the
lack of information or lack of their
intelligence to understand it's because
of the the lack of the sufficient basis
of of that morality virtue
accomplishment solitude sign of the mind
guarding of the sense doors
because if that basis is thoroughly
developed very little instruction will
be necessary to to understand the
not-self and then cultivate it further it's like
and then cultivate it further it's like
that that idea of not self
uh a person can get that idea that
theory and it remains a theory until you
actually live in accordance with that
idea yeah and even as a theory as i said
it can have a you know
it can be a theoretical to some degree
but it have its practical side of it
but that practicality is something you
don't want to um
you don't want to be sort of uh
living off of it
so to speak so if you had some like a
practical release
fine now have thousand more of those
it's not about having one i mean the
buddha said to even even the actual
sotapannas actual sakuragamis actual
actual undergarments he said did you
understand the dhamma for the sake of
cherishing that view that you have
or for the sake of abandoning even that
through your repetitive work and
diligence until you have crossed the
shore and says no it's for understanding so
and says no it's for understanding so
then keep digging don't don't stop
because you're on a gummy now or
something keep digging and don't carry that raft
keep digging and don't carry that raft
with you when you cross the shore then
that's it it's for that purpose
continue that renunciation exactly so so
if you have it if you if you if you've
had any kind of insight of any kind sure
now thousand times more repeat the same
and then when you do
just keep doing it
and keep increasing it and you'll know
when to stop
yeah it's like that
it's like that
you get the the right idea but then you
need to
it needs to root itself yeah you know
you bring it into reality you bring it
into realization you need to cultivate
it you might plant the best seeds
but unless you look after and clear the
weeds and then protect it from to
becoming too dry or too wet
they're not going to germinate properly
or they will not be as good so you have
to attend to it you have to keep doing
it and keep an eye on it
so what do i do next it's more like how
do i do more of this
even increase the quality of what i've
been doing but but
that
how to do more of that those
instructions are already there well
exactly how they do more of this means i
already know how i've done this so now
just do more of it
it's not a secret it's more like on the
level of diligence work repetition and
sticking to it
and yes not living off on the that kind
of
i had this experience year ago
it was power nobody denies that people
have experiences
well you deny what we what i deny is
basically the view that you can just now assume
the view that you can just now assume
it's finished or something because you
saw it once
yeah but i had experience it was real
yeah sure
but you also had experience of suffering
millions of times and he was equally
real so which is more now
so which is more now
your one experience of release
or every single time you still suffer
so there you go that's your answer can
you still suffer yes
keep then regenerating cultivating that
experience in ourself
uh if it's not clear clarified that's
your work
if it's clear then sustain it in its
clarity protect it
and make sure the virtue is there to
match to sustain that basis
uh sense restraint don't become careless
and keep doing it
you keep polishing polishing publishing
because i like that realization
realization bring it
you you're bringing it into reality yeah
yeah yeah yeah
literal meaning or yeah exactly so it's
like an insight but then you just well
that's what bhavana is
keeping it alive
keeping it in the beam bringing it into
the actuality the being of it
sustaining it in its existence whatever
you're cultivating
until it takes
well you'll know as i say when to stop
you don't stop by decision to stop
you stop when there's no more work to be
done and you don't need to decide that that
and you don't need to decide that that
just happens
so the other
question from another friend
from another friend
he or she says
i've reached a point where i can clearly
see a rising feelings
and thoughts as not mine and simply just
as a risen
phenomenon but sometimes i lapse in
mindfulness i lose the correct
perspective and suffer as a result
also i think every time a feeling comes
up there is a self bundled with it sure
it takes about a second for me to
realize it's a nietzsche
that's too long
so i'm wondering if i've reached the
sotapanna stage if i haven't how far do
i have to go right
well if you're wondering whether you have
if you're wondering whether you have
reached it you haven't
because if you need somebody else to answer it
if you need somebody else to answer it
means you don't know it for yourself
like you just said it once you finish
the work you know exactly it's not it's
not gonna it's not like oh i can stop
now because i'm a saute pan it's more
like no it's because i'm sort of on i just
no it's because i'm sort of on i just
the work cannot happen anymore because
there's no more work
to that extent
so then you keep looking for work and
there is no more work and then you calm
down and then you realize there is no
more work
that's how soothers always describe it
as well he works diligently it's not
like oh is this handle worn out yet no
he just uses the handle until he
realizes he's worn out and then it needs
to be replaced so saying the uh a monk
just purifies his mind purifies his mind
purifies his mind he doesn't oh when
will i
not will i am i he just keeps doing it
keeps doing he keeps doing it then when
there's no work to done he just
obviously has to drop it and calm down
and then when the on the later occasion
when his mind calms down as i said to
say he realizes oh the mind's free or
freer um um
so
if you're asking if you're a soda panna
means you're not that doesn't mean what
you're doing is wrong
it just means you have to keep doing it
more until basically you are unable to
suffer amidst things that are making you suffer
amidst things that are making you suffer
and then whether the whole world says
you are sativa her you're not so upon it
doesn't matter you went beyond suffering
to that extent
and the the reason why
the the reason why
um
that person cannot sustain mindfulness
or rather mindfulness lapse and then
they suffer
because they lose perspective
it's because the mind hasn't been
developed enough
and you don't develop mind enough by
getting more information that can help
you develop the mind by sense restraint
and upgrading the virtue
so that's the work that's what would
have said you know if if
a monk keeps patimoka dwells restrained
moderate in eating gaza sends those
the mind becomes pliable
as a result of that training and taming
so what he thinks then the mind will go
but he thinks it and and he will be in
control of it not other way around
because that person obviously doesn't
want to be losing the perspective
because when they do they're aware
suffering arises and persist
which means
if it were up to them
the mind would not lose the perspective
so the mind doesn't listen to them the
mind is perspective
why can the mind do that is because you
still give in to the choices that enable
mind to have control over you not other
way around so the mind is not tangible
so whenever you can't sustain what you
understood or you're lapsing or you're
getting distracted is because you still
keep choosing things rooted in creed
aversion and delusion
and and you are still acting out of
distraction
so you need to you need to upgrade the
precept or take them a bit more seriously
or take them a bit more seriously
tightly and also guard the sensors
and then
if you can't do that then you have to
accept the outcome then the mind will
get out of your control every now and
then and you will suffer and that
suffering will be worse
than somebody who is not aware of the
right context
because ignorance is bliss to a degree
that's where people do not see the
suffering and sensuality and remain
infatuated for the rest of their life
they pay the price later much worse
price but somebody who is aware and who loses
but somebody who is aware and who loses
perspective that suffering will be felt
worse because
because
they are aware of it
and so then the the the compromise of
not being sufficiently restrained
also then has more weight so you realize
yeah it is up to you
and there's no excuse so if your mind is
not in your control it's because you
haven't tamed it enough